Preliminary Guide to the Norine Shipley Norris Papers, 1895-2000 RL.00954
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Norine Shipley Norris papers
1895-2000
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Norris, Norine Shipley
RL.00954
1.8 Linear Feet
Norine Shipley Norris attended Southern Female College (also known as Cox College) in 1897-1899, and taught Sunday school in Atlanta at Kirkwood Baptist Church in the early 1900s. This collection (2009-0129) (200 items; 1.8 lin. ft.; dated 1890s-2000) includes a variety of materials from Norine Shipley Norris, in particular her school notebooks, correspondence, and catalogs from the Southern Female College, which she attended for at least two years. Of note is the correspondence from Earnest Sevier Cox, a white supremist who courted Shipley for a time (1905-1906); photographs and records from her years of teaching at Kirkwood Baptist Church (1901-1904); and her handwritten application to the Daughters of the American Revolution (1918). Also included are a number of photographs and tintypes, scrapbooks, several books of poetry and literature, and miscellaneous clippings and ephemera.
200 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Norine Shipley Norris Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2009.
Biographical Note
Norine Shipley Norris was born in Conyers, Georgia, the daughter of Sarah Armistead and R.J. Shipley. Not much is known about the events of her life, but she did attend Southern Female College for at least two years, in 1897-1899; she also taught at the Kirkwood Baptist Church in the early 1900s. She was courted by Earnest Sevier Cox around that same time. She married James P. Norris on January 12, 1909, and appears to have lived most of her life in the Atlanta area.
Collection Overview
This collection (2009-0129) (200 items; 1.8 lin. ft.; dated 1890s-2000) includes a variety of materials from Norine Shipley Norris, in particular her school notebooks, correspondence, and catalogs from the Southern Female College, which she attended for at least two years. Of note is the correspondence from Earnest Sevier Cox, a white supremist who courted Shipley for a time (1905-1906); photographs and records from her years of teaching at Kirkwood Baptist Church (1901-1904); and her handwritten application to the Daughters of the American Revolution (1918). Also included are a number of photographs and tintypes, scrapbooks, several books of poetry and literature, and miscellaneous clippings and ephemera.
Related Material
Earnest Sevier Cox Papers
Duke University
Books; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Atlanta (Ga.); African Americans -- Segregation; Women's institutes -- 19th century; Baptist universities and colleges -- United States -- 19th century; Clippings (information artifacts); United States -- Race relations; Norris, Norine Shipley; Norris, Norine Shipley; Cox, Earnest Sevier; Daughters of the American Revolution; Southern Female College
- Accession (2009-0129), 3 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  This collection (2009-0129) (200 items; 1.8 lin. ft.; dated 1890s-2000) includes a variety of materials from Norine Shipley Norris, in particular her school notebooks, correspondence, and catalogs from the Southern Female College, which she attended for at least two years. Of note is the correspondence from Earnest Sevier Cox, a white supremist who courted Shipley for a time (1905-1906); photographs and records from her years of teaching at Kirkwood Baptist Church (1901-1904); and her handwritten application to the Daughters of the American Revolution (1918). Also included are a number of photographs and tintypes, scrapbooks, several books of poetry and literature, and miscellaneous clippings and ephemera.
  - Earnest Sevier Cox correspondence, 1905-1906 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1900s (Box 1)
  - Kirkwood Baptist Church Sunday school class, 1901-1904 (Box 1)
  - Norrine's notebooks: College Looseleaf scrapbook clippings inserts (Box 1)
  - Norine's notebooks (3) (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - General (Box 1)
    - Preachers (Box 1)
    - Shipley photographs (Box 1)
    - Armsted photographs (Box 1)
    - No label (Box 1)
  - Angie Norris Hauser, 2000 (Box 2)
  - Angie Norris Hauser tintypes and autograph book (Box 2)
  - Books
    - Riley, James Whitcome: An Old Sweetheart of Mine, 1902 (Box 2)
      Book of poetry given to Norine Egbert Shipley by Earnest Sevier Cox, Dec. 25, 1904.
    - Clay, John Cecil: In Love's Garden (Box 2)
      Book of poetry given to Norine Egbert Shipley by Earnest Sevier Cox, Dec. 25, 1905.
    - Gray, James M.: Synthetic Bible Studies, 1900 (Box 2)
    - Painter, F.V.N.: Introduction to American Literature, 1897 (Box 2)
    - Mack, Anna E.: Heaven's Distant Lamps, 1900 (Box 2)
    - Eleventh International Sunday School Convention: The Development of the Sunday School, 1780-1905, 1905 (Box 2)
    - The Poems and Drama of Lord Byron, 1884 (Box 2)
    - Hamill, H.M.: Practical Outline: Study of the Four Gospels; Life of Christ; Acts, 1904 (Box 2)
    - Alfred, Lord Tennyson: The Princess (Box 2)
      From E.S. Cox.
    - Longfellow's Complete Poems, 1898 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, Norine Shipley, J.P. Norris, 1900s-1940s (Box 3)
  - Southern Female College reports, 1897-1899 (Box 3)
  - Daughters of the American Revolution application, 1918 (Box 3)
  - Photographs
    - Family (Box 3)
    - Unknown (Box 3)
    - Daniels and McDaniels family (Box 3)
    - Landscapes (Box 3)
  - Coloring book scraps, James Hauser (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous commericial advertisements and materials, 1910s-1930s (Box 3)
  - Clippings, notecards, scraps, 1900s-1930s (Box 3)
  - Poems of Edgar Allen Poe, 1882 (Box 3)
  - Lamb, Charles and Mary: Tales from Shakespeare, 1807 (Box 3)
  - Above the Clouds of Old New York (Woolworth Building tower), 1913 (Box 3)
  - Environs of Cox College and Conservatory, College Park, Georgia, 1907 (Box Oversize 16)
  - Portraits (2) (Box 3)